Guide to the Robert K. Massie Papers Relating to Nicholas and Alexandra
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Robert K. Massie papers relating to Nicholas and Alexandra
1964-1968
GEN MSS 775
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.5
(13 boxes)
The papers are comprised of Robert Massie's original typescript, setting typescript, galley proofs, and page proofs for his book Nicholas and Alexandra (New York: Atheneum, 1967). Also present are some of his research notes, clippings and reviews of the publication, and three letters regarding the placement of these papers. Box 9 contains the original typescript of Massie's earliest version of the work, titled "The Last Days of the Romanovs," dating from 1964.
Massie, Robert K., 1929-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Robert K. Massie, 1968.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Robert K. Massie (1929- )
Robert Kinloch Massie III was born in Lexington, Kentucky, in 1929. He was a graduate of Yale University (1950) and Oxford University (1952), where he was a Rhodes scholar. Massie began his literary career as a journalist writing for Collier's (1955-1956), Newsweek (1956-1962), and the Saturday Evening Post (1962-1965), and later taught at Princeton University and Tulane University. Massie's interest in the Romanov family stemmed from his personal research on hemophilia, a hereditary and incurable blood disease that afflicted his young son Robert IV, as it had Alexei Romanov, who had inherited it through his mother, the Empress Alexandra. Massie's first work in Russian history, Nicholas and Alexandra (New York: Atheneum, 1967) was followed by Peter the Great: His Life and World (New York: Knopf, 1980), and The Romanovs: The Final Chapter (New York: Random House, 1995).
Scope and Contents
The papers are comprised of Robert Massie's original typescript with revisions, setting typescript with additional corrections and editing, galley proofs with corrections, and page proofs with corrections for his book Nicholas and Alexandra. Also present are some typed research notes and reviews of the book, as well as three letters regarding the disposition of these papers, from Boston University Library (1967), to Beinecke Library (1968) and to Murray Frank (1968). Box 9 contains the original typescript of Massie's earliest version of the book, titled "The Last Days of the Romanovs" and dating from 1964.
Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Russia -- History -- Nicholas II, 1894-1917; Russia -- Kings and rulers -- Biography; Russia -- Politics and government -- 1894-1917; Alexandra, Empress, consort of Nicholas II, Emperor of Russia, 1872-1918; Massie, Robert K., 1929-; Massie, Robert K., 1929- ( Nicholas and Alexandra); Nicholas, Emperor of Russia, II, 1868-1918
- Papers relating to Nicholas and Alexandra
  Arrangement
  Arranged largely in chronological order.
  - Original typescript with manuscript corrections and additions, chapters 1-18, 1966; 5 (Box 1)
  - Original typescript with manuscript corrections and additions, chapters 19-34, and epilogue, 1966; 5 (Box 2)
  - Typescript (carbon, with some photocopy insertions) annotated with source material, chapters 1-24, 1966; 5 (Box 3)
  - Typescript (carbon, with some photocopy insertions) annotated with source material, chapters 25-34, and epilogue, 1966; 3 (Box 4)
  - Typescript as presented to Atheneum Publishing Company in January 1967, with corrections by the author and printer's layout notations. Accompanied with 91 pages of preliminary material, chapters 1-19, 4 (Box 5)
  - Typescript as presented to Atheneum Publishing Company in January 1967, with corrections by the author and printer's layout notations, chapters 20-34, and epilogue, 2 (Box 6)
  - Photocopy of complete typescript presented to Atheneum Publishing Company, 1967; 2 (Box 7)
  - Author's first galley proof with manuscript corrections and author's first page proofs with manuscript corrections, 1967; 2 (Box 8)
  - Uncorrected galley proof, and typescript of "The Last Days of the Romanovs", 1964, 1967; 2 (Box 9)
  - Typescript research notes arranged by chapter, chapters 20 and 22, undated; 3 (Box 10)
  - Typescript research notes arranged by chapter, chapters 23-28, undated; 5 (Box 11)
  - Typescript research notes arranged by chapter, chapters 29-34, undated; 6 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, and miscellaneous newspaper clippings and advertisements relating to Nicholas and Alexandra, 1967-1968 (Box 13)